#### **RISHABH JAIN**

Phone: +91-7019690779 +91-9899193835

⊠ : jainrishabh657@gmail.com

#### **Professional Summary**

Professional Data Engineer with 5+ years of industry experience. Expertise in ETL development, automation tools and E2E life cycle of software design process. Outstanding communication skills, dedicated to maintain up-to-date IT skills and industry knowledge.

## **Career Conspectus**

- Having 5+ years of experience in ETL using IBM InfoSphere DataStage 11.X for designing, developing, scheduling and testing jobs using DataStage Designer, DataStage Director. Also have brief experience in Administration related activities.
- Experience and knowledge in Data warehousing application development using Data Vault methodology and Dimensional Modelling.
- Designed and maintained E2E data pipeline using Big Data Technologies like **Sqoop**, **PySpark** and **Redshift**.
- Experience in designing, developing and testing of ETL jobs. Data mappings in Parallel jobs using DataStage to populate tables in Data Warehouse and Data mart.
- Experience in designing Parallel jobs using various stages like Join, Merge, Lookup, Remove duplicates, Filter, Aggregator, Transformer, etc.
- Used Director and Control-M for Validating, Running, Monitoring and scheduling of jobs etc.
- Well-versed knowledge in Oracle using SQL developer tools.

## **Technical Skill**

- ETL Tools IBM InfoSphere DataStage 11.5, 11.7, 11.3
- Database Oracle SQL Developer, Hive
- Scheduling tool Control-M
- Operating System UNIX AIX 5.3, Linux and Windows Flavours
- Version controlling tool Stash Portal and SourceTree
- Language Python (Numpy and Pandas)
- Data Visualization: Matplotlib and Seaborn
- Cloud Service EC2, S3 and Redshift (AWS)
- Data Ingestion Sqoop
- Apache Spark

# **Work Experience**

Company : Accenture Solutions Pvt Ltd(deployed on Client Location)

Duration : Nov 2019 – Till DateDesignation : Data Engineer

2. Company : Harjai Computers Pvt Ltd(deployed on Client Location)

**Duration** : Jun 2019 – Nov 2019 **Designation** : ETL Developer

3. Company : NetAnalytiks Technologies (deployed on Client Location)

**Duration** : Feb 2019 – Jun 2019 **Designation** : ETL Developer

: Mphasis Ltd. 4. Company

> : Feb 2016 - Feb 2019 Duration

Designation : Delivery Software Engineer

# **Roles & Responsibilities**

Worked on Migration project from 7.3 to 11.3 DS Environments which eventually saved approx \$2.5 M through this transition. Also worked on Migration from DS 8.7 to 11.7.

- Ingested data from disparate data sources using Sqoop into Hadoop File Storage system to create data views to be used by different users.
- Designed and implemented a data pipeline to process different types of data by integrating millions of raw records from data sources using PySpark and stored processed data in Redshift.
- Maintained data pipeline up-time of 99.9% while ingesting transactional data across several different primary data sources using Spark, Redshift, S3, and Python.
- Extensively used DataStage Designer to develop jobs for extracting, transforming, integrating and loading data into target tables.
- SME of numerous critical activities which includes **Datastage Admin** related tasks.
- Optimized Existing code and reduced daily load time to more than 40% which resulted in job completion within SLA.
- Being a key resource of the team, mentored the new joinee with the existing process along with my allocated tasks.
- Involved in migration of on-premise application to AWS.
- Worked on EC2 and S3 bucket to load data files and load it into Hive.
- Developed Jobs in **Datastage** for loading data from downstream source till reporting.
- Used Control-M scheduling tool to monitor the jobs and resolved Production issues without any escalation.
- Ran lineage reports using Metadata Workbench of Information Governance Catalog (IGC).
- Involved with BA's in providing strategic reporting to customers.
- Worked in full fledged Agile methodology.

## **Certification & Accomplishments**

- AWS certified Solutions Architect Associate in 2020.
- Sumo Logic Certified in Fundamentals in 2020.
- Cleared Pega CSA72V1 exam with 91% and hold a certified Pega 7.2 System Architect Certificate in 2016.
- Have received multiple **Client appreciation** on the delivery perspective.
- Have received **Employee of the month award**.
- 6 weeks training in R&D of PRASAR BHARTI DOORDARSHAN in 2013.
- 6 weeks training of EMBEDDED SYSTEM (using avr) in 2014.

### **Education**

Exam	School/College	Board/University	Year of	Marks Obtained
			Passing	(%)
M.S Data	Liverpool John Moores University	Liverpool John Moores	2022	(Pursuing)
Science		University		
PGD in Data	International Institute of	International Institute of	2021	(Pursuing)
Science	Information Technology Bangalore	Information Technology		
		Bangalore		
B.Tech	Noida Institute of Engineering and	Uttar Pradesh Technical	2015	70
(ECE)	Technology, Greater Noida(U.P.)	University		
12 <sup>th</sup>	BBPS, Delhi	C.B.S.E	2011	80
10 <sup>th</sup>	NWPS, Lucknow(U.P.)	C.B.S.E	2009	72